NICHOLAS HOYT

SUMMARY

Software designer and developer specializing in UX/UI design and front end development.

Over twenty years of experience in user interface design and software development with a focus on financial tools, browser extensions and web application user experience design.

Expertise in interaction design, conceptual models, usability testing and analysis and web accessibility evaluation. Significant experience with modern JavaScript, HTML & CSS.

See also my online <u>UX/UI design portfolio</u> at nicholashoyt.com/portfolio.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Interaction Designer / Software Developer University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign Sept. 2005 - present

Lead designer and developer of the Skip to Landmarks and Headings browser extension, which provides a menu for easy navigation to the ARIA landmark regions and HTML section headings of a web page. Developed using Web Components and WebExtensions APIs; both a <u>Chrome version</u> and a <u>Firefox version</u> are available.

Lead designer and developer of CKEditor plugins for the A11yFirst Project. The five plugins, Heading/Paragraph, Image, Link, Character Style and Help, were thoroughly tested for usability, and are available for download at CKEditor Add-ons.

Lead designer and contributing developer of AInspector WCAG, a Firefox browser extension that provides web accessibility evaluation based on the WCAG, ARIA and HTML 5 specifications; available at <u>Firefox Browser Add-ons</u>.

Lead designer and developer of the <u>Accessibility Bookmarklets</u>, which are web accessibility visualization tools compatible with all major browsers and available at accessibility-bookmarklets.org; developed in collaboration with the consulting firm Pixo.

Lead designer and contributing developer of the <u>Functional Accessibility Evaluator</u>, a Django/Python web application that uses web crawling to evaluate the accessibility of websites based on requirements in WCAG, ARIA and HTML 5.

Interaction Designer / Front End Developer Web UI, Wheaton, IL Aug. 1999 - Sept. 2005

As principal of Web UI, Inc., provided software design and development services with an emphasis on interaction design and front end development for various corporate clients, including ABN AMRO, Accenture, Allstate Insurance, DeVry University, Fidelity Investments, HOLT Value Associates and the Illinois Institute of Technology.

NICHOLAS HOYT

Projects for these clients included:

- Developing feature enhancements for web-based financial tools
- Authoring an ebook on XML/XSLT for web developers
- Teaching Webmaster Certificate and Java Programming courses
- Developing an XML/XSLT publishing system for online content
- Designing the user interface for a stock value search application
- Designing the user interface for a call center resource search application

Interaction Designer / Front End Developer Fidelity Investments, Marlborough, MA Aug. 1997 - Aug. 1999

Served as principal interaction designer in the redesign of NetBenefits, a web application providing retirement savings account access to over one million customers. Improved the user experience through contextual inquiry, task flow analysis and usability testing.

According to an article published in the *New York Times*, in the year following the deployment of the new design of NetBenefits, the number of retirement savings account customer service calls was reduced by over 50 percent compared to the previous year.

Designed and developed retirement investing tools for 401k.com, Fidelity's website for institutional investors. Tools included the Contribution Calculator, Withdrawal Calculator and Take Home Pay Calculator.

User Interface Designer / Senior Software Engineer BGS Systems, Waltham, MA July 1991 - Aug. 1997

Responsible for the user interface design and development of BEST/1 capacity planning and performance analysis products, using X Window / Motif on the Unix and VMS platforms. Completed the training course provided by Digital Equipment Corp. on using the X Window / Motif toolkit for building user interfaces for DECwindows.

EDUCATION

University of Massachusetts Boston BA in Computer Science with Distinction, Summa Cum Laude, 1991

Harvard Extension School, Cambridge, MA Introductory Computer Science courses

Berklee College of Music, Boston, MA Jazz Composition & Arranging major

NICHOLAS HOYT

SKILLS

Interaction Design

Requirements gathering and analysis; development of conceptual models, personas, scenarios, essential use cases, user role- and task-models; creation of wireframes using Sketch, OmniGraffle and Visio

User Research & Information Architecture

Field observations, contextual interviews, task-modeling workshops, wants and needs analysis, card sorting exercises, focus groups, paper prototyping, low-fidelity prototypes

Usability Analysis & Testing

Creation of interactive HTML/JavaScript prototypes, task lists and surveys for testing; facilitation of remote and lab-based usability testing; quantitative and qualitative analysis of test results

Front End Development

Modern JavaScript (ES6 and later), HTML, CSS, DOM scripting, WCAG accessibility requirements, responsive design, Web Components, Chrome and Firefox browser extensions, WebExtensions API, Adobe Photoshop, experience with React

Web Development

Node, npm, Babel, Webpack, Gulp, Rollup, JavaScript, XML/XSLT, Django, Python

CONTACT INFO

<u>LinkedIn Profile</u> — Additional details available upon request